<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Graduate Math Modelling in Industry - 2016</title>
 <link href="http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/"/>
 <updated>2016-08-11T14:07:32-07:00</updated>
 <id>http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh</id>
 <author>
   <name>Mark Otto</name>
   <email>markdotto@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>GMMIW Project 1 Update</title>
   <link href="http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/project/2016/08/11/project1/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-11T13:22:01-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/project/2016/08/11/project1</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;project-1-stochastic-modelling-for-hydro&quot;&gt;Project 1: Stochastic modelling for hydro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mentor-fabian-bastin-university-of-montreal&quot;&gt;Mentor: Fabian Bastin, &lt;em&gt;University of Montreal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ninety-five percent of Quebec’s Electricity Comes from Hydropower! How the water is used depends on demand (Provincial and American), how much water is currently stored in the reservoir behind the dam, and how much water we expect in the future. If only we knew the future … or were at least able to make an educated guess about the future, we could use optimization schemes to make a choice about how to handle the water,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/barrage-daniel-johnson-lrg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hyrdro-electric dam&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately…. there is a lot of uncertainty in river/reservoir inflows! Our goal is to  create a stochastic method to estimate inflows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dam4_plot.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Variability in water flow&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we have a stochastic method, we will use it to create simulations for a simplified system of dams including three reservoirs and four dams/generators. 
The simulations will incorporate&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Julia programming language&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the CPLEX optimizer, with previous work from the University of Montreal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using scenred2 (GAMS) to create scenario trees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/arbre.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Scenario tree&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At each time-step the simulation will&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;create a scenario tree using a large amount of synthetic series created via the stochastic process.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;based on the current state of the system and the scenario tree, the optimizer will create a decision vector.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;progress to the next time step according to the formula:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vol(new) = Vol(prev) + inflows + Vol(upstream) − Vol(turbine) − Vol(spill).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simulation tool will allow us, or future users, to test and validate different optimizers and stochastic methods!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>GMMIW Mid Week Reports</title>
   <link href="http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/2016/08/10/gmmiw-mid-week-reports/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-10T16:22:03-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/2016/08/10/gmmiw-mid-week-reports</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s only been two days, but we can’t wait to hear what you’ve been doing!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Group 4 visits the Chan Center</title>
   <link href="http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/2016/08/09/group4-chan-center/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-09T16:54:01-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/2016/08/09/group4-chan-center</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Group 4, took a trip to the Chan Center&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/group4-chan-center.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chan Center Visit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pimsmath/status/763115330348527617&quot;&gt;@pimsmath&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>GMMIW Project 6</title>
   <link href="http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/project/2016/08/07/project6/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-07T00:22:06-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/project/2016/08/07/project6</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;project-6-modelling-and-optimisation-of-traffic-light-signals&quot;&gt;Project 6: Modelling and optimisation of traffic light signals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mentor-chris-budd--university-of-bath-uk&quot;&gt;Mentor: Chris Budd,  &lt;em&gt;University of Bath, UK&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Description:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traffic flow through a city is an important problem for transport planners; traffic jams can have serious economic implications both for the individuals stuck in the jams and the businesses that lose time and revenue as a result. Traffic light signalling is a crucial part of maintaining a good traffic flow and robust algorithms are needed to determine the signal timings. As flow rates increase during peak times, poorly chosen timings will cause the breakdown of the flow, and hence create a traffic jam. Well chosen timings will allow higher flow rates and hence delay the breakdown of the flow, potentially avoiding a traffic jam altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although many junctions are equipped with traffic sensors in the form of inductance loops buried in the road, a large number of traffic lights are still operated on a fixed timing system. (The fixed times may change throughout the day.) To determine the timings, historical traffic flow data is used. Robust methods are needed to determine appropriate timings given uncertainties in the flow rates.
A further level of sophistication comes when sensor input is available to the traffic light signalling software. The idea is that with accurate arrival data, signal timings can be chosen optimally. Moreover, GPS data from buses and other vehicles on the road may be used to give forecasts of future arrivals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desired background for students working in this project include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Differential equations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Numerical methods&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perhaps some stochastic methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>GMMIW Project 5</title>
   <link href="http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/project/2016/08/07/project5/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-07T00:22:05-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/project/2016/08/07/project5</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;project-5-modelling-the-performance-of-rechargeable-li-ion-batteries&quot;&gt;Project 5: Modelling the performance of rechargeable Li-Ion batteries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mentor-brian-wetton-university-of-british-columbia&quot;&gt;Mentor: Brian Wetton, &lt;em&gt;University of British Columbia&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Description:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rechargeable batteries are now standard components in electronic devices and are becoming more widely used in electric vehicles. Lithium ion batteries are one of the most popular types for both of these applications. They have high energy density and a long shelf life, are cheap to construct, and are safe to store and operate (all in comparison to other battery types). In these batteries, energy is stored when Lithium ions enter a solid electrode of layered material. Basic information about Lithium ion batteries can be found, on Wikipedia and at http://batteryuniversity.com/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project will explore the modelling of small scale Lithium ion batteries for electronic devices. Using experimental data on charging and discharging cycles, we will develop virtual battery simulation tools to predict performance in varying conditions and to develop optimal charging strategies. Models will begin with simple black box (system identification) and equivalent circuit models and can be extended to include more physics and chemistry. As time permits, we can consider using the simulation tools to investigate charging and operation of batteries with different characteristics arranged in parallel and series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students may measure battery performance themselves using simple electronic equipment, if time and resources permit. As a backup plan, the experimental data used to develop the models will be taken from the manufacturer’s data and scientific literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desired background for students working in this project include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Differential equations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Numerical methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>GMMIW Project 4</title>
   <link href="http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/project/2016/08/07/project4/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-07T00:22:04-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/project/2016/08/07/project4</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;project-4-this-party-is-too-big-folks-setting-room-capacities-for-safety&quot;&gt;Project 4: This party is too big, folks! Setting room capacities for safety.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mentor-nilima-nigam-simon-fraser-university&quot;&gt;Mentor: Nilima Nigam, &lt;em&gt;Simon Fraser University&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Description:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most rooms for public gatherings will have signage about the maximum lawful capacity of people in the room. Similarly, elevators state a maximum number of people. In this project, the students’ task is to develop a mathematical model to determine the maximum lawful capacity for the Chan Shun Concert Hall in the Chan Centre for the Performing Arts at UBC. Similarly, the students will determine the maximum allowable number of people in the elevators leading to the Chan Centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An initial focus is to consider what factors may be important. Layout? Access to exits? Speeds of humans? Seating arrangements? Remember that the Chan Shun Concert Hall has several options for configuration. Would one want to change the maximum lawful capacity in these cases? How will these proposed answers in the project compare to the technical specifications for the venue? Any mathematical model needs to be explicit about any simplifying assumptions and scaling arguments used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a more sophisticated variant, suppose the VSO schedules a performance of music aimed at children under 18 months, who are accompanied by at least one adult each. Assume the seats in the Chan Shun Concert Hall can be moved, and that each child will be in a stroller. Determine the maximum capacity of the venue in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With very high probability, if the results of this project determine the lawful capacity is lower than what is stated on the Chan Centre’s website, the students can expect their results to be challenged! The final report needs to include a short statement to the public, defending your model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desired background for students working in this project include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discrete mathematics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Statistics and/or stochastics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Numerical modeling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>GMMIW Project 3</title>
   <link href="http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/project/2016/08/07/project3/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-07T00:22:03-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/project/2016/08/07/project3</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;project-3-growth-of-nanoparticles-for-industrial-production&quot;&gt;Project 3: Growth of nanoparticles for industrial production&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mentor-tim-myers-centre-de-recerca-matemtica-barcelona&quot;&gt;Mentor: Tim Myers, &lt;em&gt;Centre de Recerca Matemàtica, Barcelona&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Description:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nanoparticles are small units of matter with dimensions in the range of 1 to 100 nanometers. They have recently become the focus of intense research due to their unique characteristics. Nanoparticles exhibit many advantageous size-dependent magnetic, electrical, chemical and optical properties, which are not observed at the macroscale. As these properties are extremely sensitive to the particle size, the ability to produce monodisperse particles that lie within a controlled size distribution is critical. In the context of nanoparticles, monodispersity typically refers to size distributions where the standard deviation is less than five percent. Applications that require uniform particles include light emitting diodes, solar energy systems, multi-terabit magnetic storage and biological imaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this project we wish to develop a mathematical model for the growth of spherical nanocrystals from solution. Once the basic model is developed we will extend it to a number of particles and determine the factors controlling the size distribution, with the goal of producing particles of a similar size. We will then look for published experimental data and attempt to fit the model to such data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desired background for students working in this project include:
* Partial differential equations
* Numerical methods
* Some physics&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>GMMIW Project 2</title>
   <link href="http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/project/2016/08/07/project2/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-07T00:22:02-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/project/2016/08/07/project2</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;project-2-variable-selection-and-statistical-prediction-for-a-fusion-reactor&quot;&gt;Project 2: Variable selection and statistical prediction for a fusion reactor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mentor-derek-bingham-simon-fraser-university&quot;&gt;Mentor: Derek Bingham, &lt;em&gt;Simon Fraser University&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Description:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Fusion is designing and testing a prototype of a nuclear fusion
reactor with the goal of creating a commercially viable, large - scale
electrical power system.  The system depends on a fundamental physical process
that requires precise control and calibration to function correctly, and needs
optimization to produce an economically viable production operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The physics and principles of operation for the device are very complex and
involved , and the prototype is surrounded by a vast array of sensors that
monitors the operation while collecting data on a wide variety of physical
parameters ( which could include temperature, density, pressure, rates of
motion, vibrations, electromagnetic fields, etc.), which are spatially and
temporally sampled at high data rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge in this project is to sort through this vast array of data and
select variables that are statistically significant in predicting the operation
of the key parts of the device .  A keen understanding of the problem of
uncovering statistical significance in a large data set will be necessary to
make progress in the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desired background for students working in this project include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Statistics and statistical tests of significance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Machine learning and numerical methods for data analysis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some physics might be beneficial&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>GMMIW Project 1</title>
   <link href="http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/project/2016/08/07/project1/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-07T00:22:01-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/project/2016/08/07/project1</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;project-1-stochastic-modelling-for-hydro&quot;&gt;Project 1: Stochastic modelling for hydro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mentor-fabian-bastin-university-of-montreal&quot;&gt;Mentor: Fabian Bastin, &lt;em&gt;University of Montreal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The operation of a hydroelectric generation facility that supplies electrical
power must balance the demands for water flow into the generators with the
availability of water in the large reservoir behind a damn. The electrical power
demand can be predicted quite accurately, but the main uncertainty in the
operation is the source of the water inflows, especially regarding the seasons.
For instance, during Winter, there is practically no inflow of water to the
reservoir, but the electrical demands are quite high.  In the Spring, when the
snow melts, large water inflows occur, while the electrical demand becomes
smaller. Various questions arise in analysing this situation, and the project
will focus on a number of issues, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the modelling of inflows, based on historical data, and the creation of
scenario trees;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the optimization of reservoirs management. This may include using the
progressive hedging algorithm, a popular but challenging technique in
stochastic programming;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the numerical simulation of the system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key goal is to develop a better way to model the uncertainty for this process.
Some initial software models for the system are available, and the student will
be looking to create better, more realistic simulation.  Desired background for
students working in this project include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stochastic processes and stochastic modeling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optimization&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Numerical methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;more-resources&quot;&gt;More resources:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cirrelt.ca/DocumentsTravail/CIRRELT&quot;&gt;https://www.cirrelt.ca/DocumentsTravail/CIRRELT&lt;/a&gt;
-&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Welcome to GMMIW 2016!</title>
   <link href="http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/2016/08/07/welcome-to-gmmiw2016/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-07T00:22:00-07:00</updated>
   <id>http://gmmiw2016.surge.sh/2016/08/07/welcome-to-gmmiw2016</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the 2016 Graduate Math Modelling in Industry Workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next week, graduate students from all over the world will gather to
work side-by-side with industry leaders. They will develop and apply their
mathematical expertise on cutting edge problems from areas such as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stochastic modelling for hydro-electric reservoir management     Fabian Bastin - University of Montreal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Variable selection problem and statistical prediction for an industrial reactor  Derek Bingham - Simon Fraser University&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Growth of nanoparticles for industrial production    Tim Myers - Centre de Recerca Matemàtica, Spain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This party is too big, folks” - Setting room capacities for safety.     Nilima Nigam - Simon Fraser University&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Modelling the performance of rechargable Li-Ion batteries    Brian Wetton - University of British Columbia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Modelling and optimisation of traffic light systems  Chris Budd - University of Bath, UK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pims.math.ca/industrial-event/160807-gmmiw&quot;&gt;GMMIW Event Page&lt;/a&gt; for full details of the problems.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
